Dorothy Provine Free Black Research Collection 139
People's Archive, MLK Library
Dorothy Provine Free Black Research Collection
1686-1997
People's Archive, MLK Library
Provine, Dorothy S.
139
11 Linear feet
11 Boxes
Arrangement
Processed without series.
Biographical / Historical
Dorothy Provine served as an archivist in the Civil Archives Division of the National Archives in Washington, D.C. Provine authored an article titled, "The Economic Position of the Free Blacks in Washington, D.C., 1800-1860." She continued her work with the release of the District of Columbia Free Negroes Register, 1821-1861. In her work, Provine compiles the abstracts of entries in the free black registries in D.C. The records cover 1821-1861, which from the early 19th century to just prior to the Civil War. The collection includes research Provine completed in order to finish her publications.
Custodial History
The collection was donated to the Library by Dorothy Provine in 1998.
Scope and Contents
The Dorothy Provine Free Black Research Collection contains photocopies of wills, marriage registers, freedom records, manumissions records, research files, writings by Provine, birth records, death records, records of social organizations, genealogy records, and records of black property owners. It should be noted that while the documents in this collection date from 1686 to 1997, nearly all records in this collection are photocopies of original documents, made predominantly in the 1990s.
African Americans; Genealogy; Registers of births, etc; Organizational Records; Real Property; Marriage records; Families; Legal documents; Slaves--Emancipation; Black people
- Series 1
  - Dorothy Provine Petitions under the Act of Apr.16,1862 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dorothy Provine Petitions under the Act of Apr.16,1862 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - PG County Index, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arlington County Free Negro Register 1797-1841 Vol. 1, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Free Negro Register - 1842-1847 Vol. 2, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Free Negro Register - 1847-1861 Vol. 3 Part I, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Free Negro Register - 1847-1861 Vol. 3 Part II, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Registration of Free Negroes - 1806-1863 PG County Maryland, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - DC Free Negro Registers - 1821-1861, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1850 Ward 4 - I 279B, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Free Blacks - MD Freedom Register - 1807 Law, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Misc, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Wards of Washington - 1846-1853, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Wills - Misc, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Population, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Prostitution "Bawdy Houses" DC List, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Prostitution "Bawdy Houses"[Coloured] DC List - 1864-1865, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ads for Runaways - Examples of 1814, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Misc- articles and book reviews, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - John Quincy Adams and Joshua Johnson, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Marriage Returns Vol. 1, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Prologue Journal of the National Archives Winter 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reuben Crandall (Trial of… 1836), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Woodlawn Sketches Calender, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Surnames: to black, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Henrietta Semmes - slave ownershiip of - will peition for reimbursement, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Will of John Taylor, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ads for Runaways - Slaves and Apprentices, 1802-1854 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Census -Database Setup (Draft), 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - St. Patriick's in Washington 1794-1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Registrations - Employment of Janey's Servant, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Stephen B. Wall Case, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Laws - Deeds of Manumission, 1812-1848 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Outbridge Horsey, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Unusual Preparations, 1686-1857 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Duty and "Fast Living" Mary Johnson Sprow Domestic Worker, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - MD. Free Blacks 17th century, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Loren Book Schweninger - " Prosperous Blacks in the South 1790-1880", undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Marriage Branch Records Inventory, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Olmsted's Out (1852), 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - DC Blacks - Terr. Gov't Shepherd, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Occupations - 1860 from 8th Census (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1860- Nativities (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Population, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tenn. Gov't (Blacks in), 1868 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Henry Robinson - "Some Aspects of the Free Negro Population of DC - 1800-1862, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1835 - Snow Riot, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pearl Affair, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Duty and Fast Living" The Diary of Mary Johnson Sprow, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Local Aspect of Slavery in DC, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - F St. Tavern Fire (1819), 1906 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Myers - Excerpts article by RCHS, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - From Tilp… This was the Potomac, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Life on the Potomac River, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Re Check, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Emancipation Day Apr. 16, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Kurtz "Emancipation" the District of Columbia Civil War History XXIV, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - The Emancipation of the Slaves in the District of Columbia, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Compensated Emancipation in DC, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - The Economic Position of the Free Negro in DC - 1800-1860, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - VA Free Black Community - McClean [Cottonwood], 1860 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - 1860 Occupations of Free Blacks from Census of 1860 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Melvin Williams - "A Blueprint for Charge: The Black Community in Wash 1860-1870, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - DC Medical Care- Reconstruction "Freedman's Hospial Camp Barker", 1898 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - L.R Items copies - Civil Rights; Racism Blacks, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Alexandria Blacks (Rosenthal Articles), undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Afro. Am. MD. Montgomery County Builders, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Afro. Am. - VA Alexandria (Eco), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Maryland History Bibliography 1993: A Selected List, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - MD Montgomery County, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Special Issue: History in Maryland the Sesquicentinnial of the Maryland Historical Society, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - 1850 Resolutions (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Wormley Family, 1879-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Alfred Jones, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Adoption in Washington [Article], 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Orphan Asylums, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Apprentices - General, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Washington Asylum, 1850 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Black Churches in DC, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Economic Position and Free Blacks DC - 1800-1860 Tour of Negro History LVIII (Jan. 1973) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Prostitution, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Free Blacks - 1821 Residency Law (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Birth Misc Info Re examples, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - William Cranch, 1855 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Messages - Mixed, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Deaths Unusual, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Jail Slave Register, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Wills - Misc. Provisions Re. Slaves "Servants", undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Licenses - List of in Newspaper, 1849-1850 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Justices of the Peace, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The U.S Sanitary Comm. In Wash 1960-1962, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Washington During the Reconstruction - 1865-1878, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Choral Society (Afri-Am.) - DC, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Proctor Washington's Past and Present Court System D.C. 1801-1928, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Naturalization Records - DC Records, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Index to Marriages/Deaths National Intelligencer, 1812-1844 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Last Will and Testaments, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - African Americans DC/ Washington from Banneker to Douglass 1791-1870, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - African Americans Wilson Quarterly Articles of 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Last Will and Testament and Census, 1860-1873 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Marriage Returns Vol. 85, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - OS to Check, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Outbridge Horsey, 1812 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Alexandria County-VA- Apprenticeships - 1808-1812, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Free Blacks - Alexandria VA, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Alexandria Population, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Work Record, 1843 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Journal of Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society Fall, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Marriages - Unusual, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Misc., undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Marriages/Births/Deaths, 1884-1895 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Petitions, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Deaths to be Filed, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mary N. Adison, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Barker Murray, 1848 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Becket/Beckett, 1879-1880 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Blackstone (Gen.), 1771 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - John Brent, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - John S. Brent (Son of John Brent), 1885 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Brogden, 1850 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Sarah E. Jenkins Robert Bushrod, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - John Cephas, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Francis Cole, 1859 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Coles, 1850 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - John F. Cook, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - John Francis Cook Jr., 1860 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - John H. Cook - 1878, 1879-1910 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Costin, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Goerge Cover, 1860 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - ,Alexander Crummel, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Elsey Curtis - Blacks Who Claimed Slaves - 1862 Case 587 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - DC Shields - Matilda 1 Dec. 1897 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - WM Dodson, 1863-1869 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Douglas/Douglass, 1907-1908 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Thomas M. Downer, 1840 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Docket to Sarah Minor, 1874 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Mrs. Mary Fernwick, 1835 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Henry Fleet, 1807 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - William Freeman, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Jacob Grant, 1848 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Thomas Garrison, 1814 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Charles Grandison, 1846-1847 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Abigail and Nellie Gray (Freed will - 1836), undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Hiram Gray, 1847 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Francis/ Elizabeth Green - Slaves Living as Free and Counted in census, 1850 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - James Edward Green, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - John Green, 1879 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Lucy Hanson, 1831 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Goerge Thomas Hanson, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Theodosia Herbert, 1864 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Alfred Lee, 1850-1864 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Rosie (Rosa) F. Lee, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Daniel Lewis, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Johnarthur Lightfoot, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - George Liverpool, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Benj. M/Ann Eliza McCoy, 1884 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Sibby Lavinua McCoy (Daughter of Benj. M McCoy), 1912 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - McCoy, 1839-1892 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Middleton, 1979-1880 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Daniel Murray, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Elsey/Jesse/John Norman, 1801-1811 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - John Ogleton, 1880 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Painter/Paynter, 1879-1898 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Penny, 1860 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - William and Virginia J. Pierre, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Albert Ridgeley, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Lucy Ross, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - James A. Savoy, 1879 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - George Seaton House, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Sarah Catherine Smith/Wife of Willis James Smith, 1884 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Jerry Snow, 1811 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Minty Snowden, 1879 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Maria Wellington Stewart, 1880 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - James Sumby, 1850 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Tuxon, 1848 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Christopher Waters, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Harriet and Gassaway Waters, 1846 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Wayman, 1850 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - George M. Winter, 1879 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - George Wise, 1817 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Woodard, 1879 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Woodland, 1850 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - John Woodward, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Wormley, 1879 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - James Wright, 1850 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Allen Josephine Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Ambush Edward Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Bailey Carrol Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Bealle Enoch Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Bean Scipio Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Beckett William Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Bell Martha E Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Bell Mary Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Bias Noah Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Bolden George Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Bowen George Perosnal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Bowie Mary Personal Data, undated (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Briscoe Palmer Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Brown Charles Free Black Papers, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Brown William Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bruce Aaron Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bryan John A. Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Burrell John Free Black Papers, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - James Butler Jr Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - John Butler Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - William Butler Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - William H. Campbell, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Dick Moses Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Douglas Henry Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Douglas Henry Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Douglas William Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - William H. Edenburg, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Basil Fletcher Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Jesse Fletcher Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - John Freeman Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Walter Freeman Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Hester Gant Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Thomas A. Gant - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Dobson James Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - George Garrison - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Hannibal Graham - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Thomas Gray - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Clarrisa Thomas - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Lucy Hamilton - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Roderick Hampton - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Roderick Hampton - HRS Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Luke Hanson - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Harley Smith - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Henry Hatton - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Anna Henderson - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Ellen Henson - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Rachel Herbert -Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - William Herbert - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Caroline Hill - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Walter Humphrey - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - David Jackson - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Thomas Jenifer - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Andrew Jenkins - Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - John Chloe Ann Personal Data, undated (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Misc- Notes A - XYZ, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Population, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Laws, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Population of Free Blacks, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Rachel Johnson - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Thomas Johnson - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Samuel Key - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Catherine Lancaster - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Catherine Lee - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - William Lee - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Primus Lemon - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - John Levy - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - James Lodge - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Thomas H. Lucas - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - George McCoy - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - John McGinnis - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Catherine Martin - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Eliza Miles - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Levi Mitchell - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Lindsay Muse - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Richard H. Nugent - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Basil Patterson - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Saumel Ramsay - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Joseph Richards - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Daniel Ross - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Harriet Saunders - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Christy Sawyer - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Leonardas Scott - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Dennis Smallwood - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - William Smith - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Charles Stewart - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Robert Stevenson - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Harriet Halbert - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Ann Thomas - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Richard Tompkins - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Stewart Truxton - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Robert Vodery - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Joseph Warren - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Phillip Wells - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Mary Winchester - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Arnold Somerville - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Edward Woodland - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Elizabeth A. Travers - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Polly Twine - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Charles Wilson - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Mary Wormley - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - J. Rodney Young - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Edward C. Younger - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Salley Younger - Personal Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - City of Washington Map, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)